motion be agreed to I Mr Speaker The
Honorable David Parker we've got a bit
of competition for this call I was very
I was very happy to stand aside and not
at all not at
all um um uh Mr Speaker the labor party
is supporting the insurance credential
supervision Amendment bill it is uh as
the minister described and is the sort
of uh housekeeping legislation that
normally finds support across the house
there are a couple cple of things that I
will uh Traverse first is uh there are a
couple of minor changes that were made
by the select committee the first as uh
the minister has outlined is just the to
extend from 3 to four months the period
in which interim financial information
must be prepared and given to the
Reserve Bank and this is now aligning
with the uh financial reporting bill
which is currently going through the
Commerce
Committee uh or has been through the
Commerce Committee the second relates to
provisional licenses it became apparent
that uh uh if a institution couldn't get
a final license because for example it
had become
insolvent uh that the uh Reserve Bank
would have lost its oversight function
because a provisional license couldn't
stay in force that obviously isn't very
sensible and so the committee recommends
that provisional licenses can stay on
foot to give the Reserve Bank some
continuing powers in respect of those
entities until such time as they either
uh uh cancel a license or uh they if
their problems can be fixed they can
move to a full license there's one other
issue Mr Speaker which is uh not
directly affected by this bill but I
think it's good to put on record um
there's a debate going on in New Zealand
at the moment as to whether the period
uh whether the uh the strength of
insurance companies and their financial
worth should be sufficient to meet a 1
in 500e event or one in 1,000 year
event uh and the reasoning that lies
behind is my understanding the move
towards a requiring them to be strong
enough to withstand the consequences of
a 1 and 1,000 year event rather than a 1
and 500 year event uh that the Alpine
fault goes once every 800 years roughly
and uh the big Quake that could hit New
Zealand or Wellington in in uh that rare
event or uh ought to be able to be um
catered For by the insurance Community
without going broke uh and effectively
leaving it to others perhaps either
putting the the onus on to private
individuals who' be left uninsured or
leaving it to the government to put to
pick up the bill this is a very
difficult decision because there are
trade-offs to be made as to whether the
additional U level of security that
would be obtained is one necessary two
affordable because if there are greater
Capital requirements required of
insurance companies then that uh that
cost will be passed on to Consumers
through the insurance bills that they
pay so the first problem uh could be
that if Insurance costs go up as a
consequence of this higher degree of
confidence that we would have that they
could meet these very expensive but
rarer events it might be that it leads
to lower levels of insurance because
people can't afford their insurance
bills so that's one issue the second
issue and this was raised with me
recently by a senior member of the
insurance industry is that if the
capital requirements uh become too high
it may be that some of the the
multinationals who are prison in New
Zealand cannot get the support from
their parent companies to provide the
additional level of capital that's
required by the New Zealand regulator
because they won't be able to get a
decent rate of return on it from the
insurance Market in New Zealand and as a
consequence some of those insurers May
withdraw from the New Zealand Market or
reduce their presence or become more
selective about the sorts of cover that
they're willing to offer because they uh
parent owning bodies overseas are not
willing to extend the additional Capital
to the New Zealand subsidiary to meet
those requirements the third problem
with it potential problem uh is that uh
if the capital barries to entry for new
entrance go even higher we are likely to
become even more dependent in New
Zealand and an important aspect of our
financial services sector namely our
insurance companies on overseas owned
companies and they will face less
competition from New Zealand owned
entities I think these are three very
important concerns and I whilst I
understand the concerns of The Reserve
Bank to improve from a credential point
of view the likelihood that insurance
companies can meet large events we have
to be very careful that we properly take
into account the three factors that I've
mentioned the cost of insurance the
likelihood that uh or the possibility
that some of the multi National insurers
will not get the capital backing
required from their parent companies to
meet those uh commitments and therefore
might withdraw from the market which
would have both a lack of competi you
know reduced competition and again could
drive up costs and also increased risks
because we'd more become more Reliant as
a country on a smaller number of
insurance companies and then the third
issue is um whether we're going to see
Ever greater Capital flows or returns of
profits from New Zealand uh Insurance
Market to overseas compan because it's
less likely that we will have New
Zealand participants in the insurance
market so that issue um uh has been
raised with by with me by uh more than
one uh representative of the insurance
industry and I believed there uh
comments to me to be unedited and not
self-interested they actually weren't uh
talking in pursuit of their own interest
they were were talking about what they
thought was in New Zealand's interest
and I I believed them to be uh to be
straight in that regard
uh so that's an issue that we've got to
Grapple with uh and uh it's a complex
one uh Mr Speaker and uh I hope that we
get that one right um m in New Zealand
um Mr Speaker uh although uh this area
of um uh Reserve Bank policy finds uh in
this bill the support of the labor party
it's fair to say that we have
considerable concern with the
effectiveness of overall Reserve Bank
Arrangements in New Zealand uh we're not
convinced that monetary policy uh is yet
right it was interesting when 3 years
ago we pulled out of the uh cross party
Accord on monetary policy that we were
accused of heresy and uh a couple of the
the things that we called for to be
changed have quietly been changed since
uh namely uh the adoption of orbe it in
a somewhat clumsy way of the uh macr
predial tools and also a discussion
paper that's now out at from the
treasury or some work that's been done
by the treasury looking at whether the
decision-making process in The Reserve
Bank should be uh the governor or
whether it should be a the board that
takes decisions relating to monetary
policy which is another change that we
called for um strange U how um these
things were heresy a couple of years ago
but when there's been true leadership
shown by the labor party even
occasionally the uh the National Party
follows so where they haven't uh what
they haven't addressed in respective
monetary policies of of course the
fundamental problem under the ACT which
is that uh Primacy has to be given by
The Reserve Bank to inflation targeting
ahead of other important aspects of
economic management that are impacted by
monetary policy including the exchange
rate uh Mr Speaker as a consequence we
have fewer jobs in New Zealand and we
have a larger current account deficit uh
which is probably New Zealand's largest
economic vulnerability much uh larger uh
CA of problems than uh the insurance
matters to which we are referring here
that is not diminish to diminish the
importance of the insurance credential
supervision Amendment bill which the
labor party
supports call Paul goldi thank you m uh
thank you Mr Speaker my pleasure to
speak on this the insurance uh
Prudential supervision Amendment Bill
and uh